<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Thesis | James Tunnell]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/categories/thesis/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamestunnell.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-07T22:25:33-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamestunnell.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Tunnell]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jamestunnell@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Proposal Is Finished]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2015/03/07/finished-proposal/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-07T14:15:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2015/03/07/finished-proposal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The last few weeks have been very productive for my thesis work. The main challenge has been leaping the intellectual hurdles in understanding the pertinant aspects of time series modeling, especially the modeling methodology. But, thanks to my newly discovered and very helpful resource on time series, Dr. Kathryn Temple, I have finally been able to talk to someone about the gory technical details. So I now have a solid, working proposal document (see the latest version <a href="https://github.com/jamestunnell/thesis/blob/master/proposal/proposal.pdf">here</a>). Now as soon as I can get a committee together, I&rsquo;ll be able to present my proposal and get this show on the road!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Git Repository for Thesis Files]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2014/11/11/thesis-repo/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-11T08:37:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2014/11/11/thesis-repo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I put all the files from my thesis work in a <a href="http://git-scm.com/">Git</a> repository. <a href="https://github.com/jamestunnell/thesis">Here is the master branch</a> at <a href="https://github.com/jamestunnell/">my GitHub account</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So as I update scripts, images, docs, etc. I&rsquo;ll commit those changes to the repo and push those commits for all to see.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More on the Thesis Proposal]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2014/11/01/more-on-thesis-proposal/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-01T03:46:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2014/11/01/more-on-thesis-proposal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve spent some time studying the high-level problem statement outlined in <a href="/blog/2014/06/25/thesis-proposal">my last post</a>), and I&rsquo;ve identified one of the main obstacles to implementing the Next Release Problem (NRP) in actual software project planning.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The obstacle stems from estimating the total cost of project requirements. Of course, the total cost will include implementation cost. But it should also include the cost of fixing software defects (bugs) that arise from the implementation. If bug fixing cost is ignored, then the total cost estimate for each requirement is inaccurate. Thus, there is not a sound sound basis for making optimization decisions involving requirement cost.</p>

<p>So, to overcome this obstacle, <a href="https://github.com/jamestunnell/thesis">my thesis work</a> will focus on providing a probabilistic model based of project historical data. The goal of the model is predicting the makeup of expected bugs resulting from any software changes. I&rsquo;m working this quarter to establish a statistical overview of actual project historical data, starting with the <a href="https://www.mongodb.org/">MongoDB</a> project.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Thesis Proposal]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2014/06/25/thesis-proposal/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-25T17:12:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2014/06/25/thesis-proposal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m writing up my proposal for the work I&rsquo;m planning to do on the Next Release Problem (NRP, see <a href="/blog/2014/06/25/next-release-problem">my previous post</a>) for my thesis. but here is a rough problem statement:</p>

<blockquote><p>For SW release planners to make use of the NRP, they need a process for mapping many raw measurements, taken from a SW project, onto the nicely abstracted space designated by the NRP.</p></blockquote>

<!-- more -->


<p>If all goes well, I&rsquo;ll have the proposal ready to present by Fall quarter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Next Release Problem]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2014/06/25/next-release-problem/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-25T16:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2014/06/25/next-release-problem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have spent a few months now trying to select a topic for my thesis, and I&rsquo;ve settled on the Next Release Problem (NRP). It&rsquo;s one of several problems being worked on in the area of Search-Based Software Engineering (SBSE). I only recently discovered SBSE while I was looking into the possibility of optimizing software development task assignment, as suggested by my thesis advisor, <a href="http://www.cwu.edu/~janvik/">Dr. John Anvik</a>. Already very energized by a recent stumbling onto Operations Research, I was glad to see it being applied in the area of SW engineering (where improvement is definitely needed).</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Next Release Problem</h3>

<p>In 2001 the Next Release Problem (NRP) was first defined by Bagnall et al<sup><a href="#Cite1">[1]</a></sup>. It addresses the need to select some subset of all the possible software improvements (features, requirements, or what have you) in order to maximize profit, while respecting an upper limit on the amount of effort that can be expended (resources) in development.</p>

<p>Now it might seem the NRP is just like a 0-1 knapsack problem at this point, but there&rsquo;s an additional consideration: profit is only achieved by satisfying a customer. Each customer can have a different profit, and a different list of enhancements that they would like to be implemented in order to be satisfied. This makes the NRP a bit more interesting. And the NRP is definitely NP-Hard, like the 0-1 knapsack optimization problem.</p>

<h4>References</h4>

<ol>
<li><a name="Cite1"/>Bagnall, Anthony J., Victor J. Rayward-Smith, and Ian M. Whittley. &ldquo;The next release problem.&rdquo; Information and software technology 43.14 (2001): 883-890.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
