<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Thesis | James Tunnell]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/categories/thesis/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamestunnell.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-27T15:09:04-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamestunnell.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Tunnell]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jamestunnell@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SEL Presentation]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2015/03/28/SEL-presentation/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-28T16:51:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2015/03/28/SEL-presentation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My Spring break started out uneventful, just relaxing with my family. Then I recieved a phone call to set up an face-to-face interview in Oregon. Great. Change of plan. Fate wasn&rsquo;t through yet, though. On my way to the interview, I got another call to set up an interview, this time with Schweitzer Engineering Labs in Pullman, WA.</p>

<p>As part of my interview, they&rsquo;ve asked me to make a technical presentation. Well, what a perfect opportunity to put together a presentation for my thesis! So I&rsquo;ve done it. It&rsquo;s long (55 slides). <a href="https://github.com/jamestunnell/thesis/blob/master/doc/presentation.pdf">Here it is</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SEKE Paper Submission]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2015/03/26/seke-paper/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-26T03:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2015/03/26/seke-paper</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Instead of pushing ahead to present my proposal, I&rsquo;ve spent the last few weeks turning the proposal into a paper (available <a href="https://github.com/jamestunnell/thesis/blob/master/doc/SEKE-paper.pdf">here on Github</a>) for submission to the Conference on Software Engineering and Knowledge Engineering (<a href="http://www.ksi.edu/seke/seke15.html">SEKE 2015</a>). This is something that I have never done before, so I&rsquo;m very grateful that I had Dr. Anvik to co-author the paper with me. The paper would probably fit well into the Measurement and Empirical Software Engineering category. But, whether the paper is accepted or not, I appreciated the chance to experience the process. And we can always improve it and resubmit to another conference.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Proposal Is Finished]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2015/03/07/finished-proposal/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-07T14:15:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2015/03/07/finished-proposal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The last few weeks have been very productive for my thesis work. The main challenge has been leaping the intellectual hurdles in understanding the pertinant aspects of time series modeling, especially the modeling methodology. But, thanks to my newly discovered and very helpful resource on time series, Dr. Kathryn Temple, I have finally been able to talk to someone about the gory technical details. So I now have a solid, working proposal document (see the latest version <a href="https://github.com/jamestunnell/thesis/blob/master/doc/proposal.pdf">here</a>). Now as soon as I can get a committee together, I&rsquo;ll be able to present my proposal and get this show on the road!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Git Repository for Thesis Files]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2014/11/11/thesis-repo/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-11T08:37:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2014/11/11/thesis-repo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I put all the files from my thesis work in a <a href="http://git-scm.com/">Git</a> repository. <a href="https://github.com/jamestunnell/thesis">Here is the master branch</a> at <a href="https://github.com/jamestunnell/">my GitHub account</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So as I update scripts, images, docs, etc. I&rsquo;ll commit those changes to the repo and push those commits for all to see.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More on the Thesis Proposal]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2014/11/01/more-on-thesis-proposal/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-01T03:46:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamestunnell.github.io/blog/2014/11/01/more-on-thesis-proposal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve spent some time studying the high-level problem statement outlined in <a href="/blog/2014/06/25/thesis-proposal">my last post</a>), and I&rsquo;ve identified one of the main obstacles to implementing the Next Release Problem (NRP) in actual software project planning.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The obstacle stems from estimating the total cost of project requirements. Of course, the total cost will include implementation cost. But it should also include the cost of fixing software defects (bugs) that arise from the implementation. If bug fixing cost is ignored, then the total cost estimate for each requirement is inaccurate. Thus, there is not a sound sound basis for making optimization decisions involving requirement cost.</p>

<p>So, to overcome this obstacle, <a href="https://github.com/jamestunnell/thesis">my thesis work</a> will focus on providing a probabilistic model based of project historical data. The goal of the model is predicting the makeup of expected bugs resulting from any software changes. I&rsquo;m working this quarter to establish a statistical overview of actual project historical data, starting with the <a href="https://www.mongodb.org/">MongoDB</a> project.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
